And we return to the hugging face open LLM leaderboard.
포옹 페이스 오픈 LLM 리더보드로 돌아가죠
The first place you go when selecting your base model for your training.
훈련용 기본 모델을 고를 때 가장 먼저 가는 곳이죠
So first thing I'm going to do is I'm going to focus in on models with a parameter size at most, let's
가장 먼저 모델에 초점을 맞추겠습니다 매개 변수 크기, 최대 9라고
say nine.
해보죠
And we can we can afford to go down a bit and let's filter out everything but the base models to start
비트만 조금 낮추고 기본 모델만 빼고 전부 걸러내죠
Um, and let's have it show the number of parameters as well.
매개 변수의 개수도 보여 주세요
Here we go in this table down below.
이 아래 테이블로 가죠
So this is the results of the strongest models according to these various metrics.
다양한 지표에 따라 가장 강력한 모델의 결과가 나왔어요
And you will see that powerhouse clan that I mentioned many times, including this 2.52.5 is very new.
제가 여러 번 언급했던 파워하우스 클랜이 보일 겁니다 이 2를 포함해서요 52살요 5는 새로운 거예요
Uh 7 billion variant.
70억 개 변종요
Uh is uh the highest scorer of this lot.
이 로드의 최고 득점자였어요
Um, and you'll see that Gemma is a 9 billion parameter variant of Gemma.
보시다시피 제마는 90억 개의 변수 제마예요
That's right up there to, uh, Mistral up here.
미스트랄강 바로 위예요
Uh, and the one that we like to talk about a lot.
우리가 자주 얘기하는 그 사람도요
Um, there was phi2, by the way, from Microsoft.
마이크로소프트의 phi2도 있었죠
Uh, llama 3.1 is a little bit further down.
라마 3요 1번 비트는 좀 더 아래예요
Uh, now it's worth mentioning that the numbers are all reasonably close at the top, although there's
먼저 언급할 점은 상위권의 숫자는 꽤 근소한 차이라는 겁니다 약간의
somewhat something of a margin here.
차이가 있긴 하지만요
Uh, so it might concern you that llama 3.1 that you happen to know is the one we're going to end up
라마 3에 대해 말씀드릴 게 있어요 여러분이 고르게 될 1은 우리가 선택하게
picking because you've seen it in the code is further down.
될 겁니다 코드에서 더 아래쪽에 있는 걸 보셨으니까요
Um, but there is there is something of a reason for that.
하지만 거기엔 이유가 있어요
Uh, when you're looking at these different scores, really you do need to, to also bring in the,
이런 다양한 스코어를 볼 때 훈련된 버전도 반드시
the versions that have been trained.
가져와야 해요
Um, the what's called the instruct variants, which are the same models but then given uh, more trained
다중 분석이라고 부르는 건 같은 모델이지만 좀 더 훈련된 형태로 다양한 강화
using various reinforcement learning techniques to to respond to that particular chat instruct style.
학습 기술을 이용해 특정 채팅 분석 스타일에 대응하는 거예요
And when it's uh, given that kind of framework, it's more likely to be able to perform against these
그런 프레임워크가 갖춰지면 다양한 테스트에 더 잘 대처할 수
various tests because it will respond to the instruction that's being given rather than being expected
있어요 주어진 지시에 반응할 테니까요 다른 작업에 적응하도록 훈련받기를
to be trained to, to adapt to a different task.
기대하기보다요
Um, so really, you're getting a more realistic view of the capability, even of the base model, if
이 기능을 좀 더 현실적으로 볼 수 있습니다 기본 모델이라도 벤치마크를
you look at how it performs with benchmarks, when you look at the instruct variation, if that makes
가지고 어떻게 작동하는지 보고 변형된 부분을 보면 이해가 되죠
sense.
그렇게 하면 라마다 3이 나오죠 제일 위에 있는 게 180억 개예요
Uh, we've got uh, Phi three is up there as well.
그 위에는 피3도 있어요
Uh, jammer.
재머요
And then um, the Meta Llama 3.1.
메타 라마 3도 있어요 1번요
So it's doing it's doing very well when you look at the instruct variant.
그러니까 instructant varian을 보면 아주 잘 되고 있어요
And as I said, uh, somewhat perversely, I'm not suggesting that we actually use the instruct variant.
좀 삐딱하게 들리겠지만 실제로 지시 기능을 쓰자는 건 아니에요
I'm suggesting that we stick with the the base version of it because we don't want it.
기본 형태를 유지하자는 거예요 그건 원하지 않으니까요
We don't want it necessarily to have used up lots of its thought process, lots of its sort of training
사고 과정이나 훈련 능력을 모두 소모하는 건 원치 않아요 시스템 프롬프트나
power, learning about things like system prompts and user prompts and so on.
사용자 프롬프트 같은 걸 배우는 것도요
I'm just saying that once you have been through that exercise, you can see it performs well in all
일단 그 훈련을 하고 나면 모든 점수가 잘 나온다는 걸 알
of these scores.
수 있어요
And that gives us a good sense that the base model is good at adapting to be able to address these different
이런 걸 보면 기본 모델이 이런 다양한 벤치마크를 해결하도록 잘 적응했다는 느낌이
benchmarks.
들죠
So that's a more nuanced way to interpret the results of the leaderboard.
순위표 결과를 해석하는 미묘한 방법이네요
You can look at the instruct variant and see how that performs, and it still gives you a good indication
변형 기능을 보고 어떻게 작동하는지 볼 수 있어요 베이스 모델이
of how the base model will perform as well.
어떻게 작동할지 알 수 있죠
Now, there is one other slightly subtle reason that that I'm picking llama, even though you might
라마를 고른 데는 또 다른 미묘한 이유가 있어요 물론 167cm인
say that either five three, Gemma or indeed Gwen would look like they are scoring higher in many fronts.
제마나 그웬이 여러 면에서 더 높아 보일 수도 있지만요
There is a convenience to llama.
라마는 편리해요
That's just.
정말 그래요
It only makes a small difference to everything, but it does make our code a bit simpler and it makes
모든 것에 약간의 차이는 주지만 코드를 좀 더 간단하게 만들고
the task a bit easier for llama, which is that when you look at the tokenizer for llama, you'll see
라마를 위한 작업을 좀 더 쉽게 해줍니다 라마를 위한 토큰라이저를 보면
that for llama, every number between 0 and 999, every three digit number gets mapped to one token.
0부터 999까지의 모든 숫자, 모든 세 자리 숫자가 하나의 토큰에 매핑되어 있는 것을 볼 수 있죠
The same is actually not true for 3 or 4, or for Quan.
3, 4편이나 콴의 경우는 달라요
In all three of those other models, they have basically a kind of you can think of it as like a token
이 세 모델 모두 기본적으로∙∙∙ 숫자당 토큰 같은 걸 갖고 있다고 생각하면
per digit.
돼요
So the number 999 ends up as three separate tokens.
999는 결국 세 개의 패가 되죠
Now, you might ask me, what difference does that make that it shouldn't make any difference at all.
이런 질문을 하실지도 모르겠네요. 그게 무슨 차이가 있죠? 전혀 차이가 없어야 하는 걸까요?
So it's going to turn out that when we're doing training we are we're using a model to generate tokens
그래서 우리가 트레이닝을 할 때 토큰을 생성하기 위해 모델을 사용합니다 회귀
and we're trying to make it think in terms of more of a regression model.
모델의 관점에서 생각하도록 하는 거죠
We want it to be trying to solve for getting better and better at predicting the next token, and that
문제를 해결하고 다음 토큰을 더 잘 예측할 수 있도록 하는 거죠 가격에도
that should map to the price.
적용되도록요
So it simplifies the problem.
문제를 단순화하죠
If the price is reflected exactly in one token that the model has to generate.
모델이 생성해야 하는 토큰 하나에 가격이 정확히 반영된다면요
So just in this particular situation, for the particular problem we're trying to solve, the tokenization
이 특정한 상황에서 우리가 해결하려는 특정한 문제에
strategy for Lambda 3.1 works very well because the the, the single next token that it generates will
대해 람다 3의 토큰화 전략이에요 1은 아주 잘 작동합니다. 생성되는 단일 다음 토큰이 가격에
in itself reflect everything about the price.
대한 모든 것을 반영하기 때문이죠
So that, uh, it's not the case that it might predict that the next token should be nine, and that
다음 토큰은 9가 되어야 한다고 예측하는 경우는 없어요 9달러,
could be $9 or $99 or $999.
999달러 혹은 999달러일 수도 있죠
And that will only transpire when it does the token.
토큰을 써야만 효과가 나타나죠
After that.
그다음에요
No, it's going to be the case that the single token that it projects as the next token in its answer
아뇨, 다음 토큰으로 제시되는 하나의 토큰이 하나의 토큰에 제품의
will reflect the full price of the product in one token.
전체 가격을 반영하는 경우죠
So it's a nuance, but it's a reason why we lean towards selecting llama 3.1 in this case.
그런 미묘한 차이 때문에 llama 3을 선택하는 거예요 이 경우엔 1명이죠
But by all means, we will have the ability to choose other models and see how they perform.
하지만 다른 모델을 선택해서 성능을 확인할 수 있어요
But llama gets a bit of an edge because of this convenience with the way that it tokenizes.
라마는 비트 마이너스가 편리해서 좀 더 유리해요
So that gives you some color on some of the thought process that goes behind selecting a model, looking
이로써 여러분은 모델을 선택하는 과정과 leaderboard를
at the leaderboards, looking a little bit more deeply at leaderboards, thinking about instruct variants
보고, 더 깊이 살펴볼 수 있습니다. 기본 모델의 매개 변수
versus the base model's parameter sizes, and then also some nuances about things like the way that
크기와 비교해 다양성을 만드는 과정과 토큰화의 작동 방식에 대한 뉘앙스를 볼
the tokenization works.
수 있죠.
And all of that together has allowed us to come to the decision that we are going to select llama 3.18
그 모든 걸 종합한 결과 이런 결정을 내릴 수 있었습니다 llama 3을 선택하기로요 180억 달러를 기본
billion as the base model for our project.
모델로 삼았어요
And now with that, let's go to the Colab and give that base model a try.
이제 Colab으로 가서 기본 모델을 시도해 보죠